Okay, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף
Daf is 118, the last דף Daf of the second to last
פרק. Perek. And we pick up with the משנה
Mishna on the bottom of קיז עמוד ב. Kuf-Yud-Zayin Amud-Bet. So let's
take a look. אחת אומרת מת, Achat Omeret Met, so we are
now dealing with all of the specifics about the belief of somebody
that testifies, this tremendous rabbinic innovation, the belief of someone that testifies,
starting with the wife but then really any single witness,
and then we're going to testify that a woman's husband has died.
And implicitly by the way, we've also said that women can testify
and not just a single witness because we talked about somebody not
being able to testify for her daughter-in-law, her mother-in-law, her step-daughter, so
generally one woman, it could be a woman, it could be a
single witness, and this is an amazing rabbinic innovation in order to
allow the woman to remarry. So we've been working through the specifics
of it. And the issue we dealt with in the last משנה
Mishna was when it was one against one or one against two
and so on, and the greater weight that the rabbis gave to
the testimony of the one that said that the man had died.
Meaning in some circumstances even if it was equal, one against one,
there's greater weight to the one who says that he had died.
That was the special belief, trustworthiness, or whatever weight of testimony that
the rabbis gave. But it also would depend on whether that testimony
had been accepted before it was contradicted or first it had been
contradicted and so on. And also two models about how that was
understood. Whether it was working within the model of testimony and one
is considered like two and then it gets the weight of real
testimony, that's the model of עולא. Ulla. And then the model of
רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah which is more like just the weight of
evidence, not testimony, and then you would go and then the numbers
on each side would be considered. So, and the גמרא Gemara tries
to sort of reconcile those two models. Now we look at the
משנה Mishna on the bottom of קיז עמוד ב. Kuf-Yud-Zayin Amud-Bet. אחת
אומרת מת ואחת אומרת לא מת. Achat Omeret Met Ve-Achat Omeret Lo
Met. One says that the husband died and one says the husband
did not die.
זו שאומרת מת תנשא ותטול כתובתה וזו שאומרת לא מת לא תנשא
ולא תטול כתובתה. Zo She-Omeret Met Tinasei Ve-Titol Ketuvatah Ve-Zo She-Omeret Lo
Met Lo Tinasei Ve-Lo Titol Ketuvatah. And now it's as clear as
not just any two women, it's actual the two co-wives of the
man. So they both said we were on a trip in Hawaii
and one came back and said he fell off the cliff and
died and the other said you're making the whole thing up, it
never happened. Okay,
so the one who says that he died is actually allowed to
remarry and the one that says not is not. So first of
all because a woman can't testify for her co-wife,
but that was one of the women that you can't testify for,
צרתה. Tzaratah. You can't testify for your co-wife. So there's two reasons
why the other woman can't. A because she contradicted her and said
that the guy's still alive, so if you say your husband's still
alive obviously can't remarry and B, and this is what the גמרא
Gemara is going to say, even if you were silent a woman
can't testify for her co-wife. Okay, but she herself can. Now that's
interesting because the implication before was if they contradicted before they came
before בית דין Beit Din accepted the testimony, it sounded like if
there was a contradiction then it would be neutralized. So we'll see
about that in the
גמרא. Gemara. אחת אומרת מת ואחת אומרת נהרג. Achat Omeret Met Ve-Achat
Omeret Neherag. Now let's say one says he died in Hawaii and
the other says he was murdered. Okay, so they're both agreeing that
he was dead, but they're just disagreeing about the particulars. Is it
seen as enough to neutralize the testimony? So רבי מאיר אומר הואיל
ומכחישות זו את זו הרי אלו לא ינשאו. Rebbe Meir Omer Ho'il
U-Makchishot Zo Et Zo Harei Elu Lo Yinase'u. Because they're contradicting, they
can't get married. So he gives somehow greater weight to the one
who says that he was murdered to undermine the testimony that he
died than if one who just says you're making the whole thing
up. You understand the difference? So תוספות Tosafot says that, well look,
if you're saying that he didn't die, so you're not believed to
say he didn't die. We said before that the testimony that somebody
died is weightier than the testimony that he didn't die. That was
the testimony the rabbis gave special weight
to. Okay, but here they're both agreeing he died. So both of
them have weight and they're just disagreeing on the specifics and that
does enough to neutralize one another. Dov, you wanted to say something?
So it's really like the rules
of עדות? Edut? I
mean we talked about whether the single woman thing is really עדות
Edut or not, but they're modeling it after I guess like there's
a difference between
הזמה Hazamah and הכחשה Hakhashah and those types of things. Yeah, so
there are some parallels with how this would play out exactly in
a world of real עדות. Edut. Okay,
so let's take a look. So that's that case. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says they do neutralize. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon אומרים היו זו וזו מודות שאין קיים ינשאו. omrim hovu zu
v'zu modus she'ein kayam yinasu. No, both of them say the husband
is dead, so both of them can get married. So as opposed
to the first case where it was a split decision, right, because
they were clearly contradictory testimonies, so you take one and you don't
take the other. Here you either reject both or you accept both.
Okay. עד אחד אומר מת ועד אחד אומר לא מת. ed echad
omer meis v'ed echad omer lo meis.
One says he died and one says he didn't and this is
not the co-wives, this is just two witnesses, right? So this is
like the case we had before in the משנה. Mishna. אשה אומרת
מת ואשה אומרת לא מת isha omeres meis v'isha omeres lo meis
or it's just two women but not the co-wives, הרי זו לא
תינשא, harei zu lo tinasei, you can't get married. That that was
implied early in the earlier משנה Mishna that when it's one and
one before it's been accepted in בית דין beis din then you
they do neutralize. If one had already been accepted in בית דין,
beis din, the one that said he dead, the second one would
not neutralize, but in this case it does. Okay, so the end
is recapping what we had sort of already figured out, but the
interesting case is the co-wives. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. טעמא ta'ama says the גמרא Gemara דאמרה לא מת. d'amrah
lo meis. The reason that the co-wife in the first case cannot
marry is because he she has explicitly said the husband my husband's
still alive. And therefore she's obviously can't go marry. האי שתיקה, hai
shtika,
if she was silent, תינשא, tinasei, the implication would be she could
go by the testimony of her co-wife. והא אין צרה מעידה לחברתה,
v'ha ein tzarah me'idah l'chavertah, but what do you mean, right? One
of the women who cannot who is not believed about the death
of a man is a woman for her co-wife, cause we figure
she's trying to like ruin her, right? So how come here, right,
how come here the משנה Mishna implies that the only reason the
co-wife can't marry is because she said the husband's alive? Right now
maybe it's you know maybe it's just that you know she can't
go marry because she can't anyway believe the testimony of the first
wife. So the גמרא Gemara says לא מת איצטריכא לה. lo meis
itztrichah lah. No, maybe I would think that if she just said
nothing then it's obvious she can't marry because she can't go by
the testimony of wife number one. But maybe ironically I would think
that if she says he's alive, she should be able to marry.
Why? That's bizarre. Why would I say that?
איצטריכא. itztrichah. סלקא דעתך אמינא המית. salka daitach amina hameis. He really
is dead and the second wife knows that as well. האי דקאמרה
לא מת, hai d'ka'amrah lo meis, why is she saying he didn't
die? לכולה לצרה היא דמכוונה. l'kulah l'tzarah hi d'michavnah. She's just trying
to make trouble for for the other one, right? So רחל Rachel
says he's dead, right,
שרה Sarah says he's not dead. So if שרה Sarah said nothing,
she can't go by רחל, Rachel, okay? Because you can't you can't
go by the testimony of a co-wife. But if שרה Sarah is
saying he's not dead, we're going to say and say to herself,
you know what, probably he is dead and she's just saying not
because she doesn't want to let רחל Rachel remarry. And even though
by saying not dead, she's going to hurt herself because she won't
be able to remarry, sometimes you're willing to hurt yourself if if
you can get back at, you know, if you can hurt somebody
else that it matters to you even more. And that and the
גמרא Gemara has a nice phrase for that. So לכולה לצרה היא
דמכוונה ותמות נפשי עם פלשתים, l'kulah l'tzarah hi d'michavnah v'tamus nafshi im
Plishtim, right, which is the language of except it's nafsha in the
פסוק, pasuk, right, which is the language of שמשון. Shimshon. Let I'll
I'm willing to die if I can pull down the stadium with
the Philistines, you know, on top of me. So it's so maybe
so because she's saying he didn't die, we're going to interpret that
as she's just doing that to spite the other wife and therefore
דוקא davka in this case it reinforces our assumption that he is
dead and therefore she should be able to be and therefore maybe
even she can remarry. Okay. קמשמע לן kamashmalan that we don't say
that, especially because we're also suspecting the first wife of of getting
herself in trouble in order to in order to get the second
wife in trouble. So anyway, fine. But whether she's silent or not,
we don't the co-wife can't get married. The other point is of
course that not only that but that the first wife is allowed
to get married, right? If one woman said died the husband died
and a a stranger said that he didn't die, that's the end
of the משנה. Mishna. That's one against one and they would neutralize.
So really part of the חידוש chiddush of this משנה Mishna is
not just that לאה Leah or whatever I said it was שרה
Sarah can't marry, part of the חידוש chiddush is that when שרה
Sarah says he's not dead, רחל Rachel can still marry, right? If
another witness said he's alive then and it was before it got
accepted in בית דין, beis din, רחל Rachel couldn't, they would have
neutralized it. But because the one who's saying he's alive is a
co-wife, we completely dismiss the testimony of a co-wife for the other
co-wife, okay? So the חידוש chiddush is not only can שרה Sarah
not marry because she can't go by רחל'ס Rachel's testimony, but רחל
Rachel is allowed to take the to marry and you completely dismiss
שרה'ס Sarah's testimony. All right, now let's say you're not going to
dismiss because each one is basically testifying for herself in a way
that she would be believed. One says died and the other said
killed. So maybe because each one is believed for herself under normal
circumstances and they also though contradict in certain ways, that maybe should
neutralize. neutralize one another. That's Rabbi Meir's position. So let's take a
look. וליפלוג רבי מאיר ברישא *veliflog Rabbi Meir bereisha*. So the Gemara
doesn't sort of see this as or initially doesn't see this as
different. If Rabbi Meir says that the co-wives can neutralize one another,
he should say it in the beginning when one says died and
the other said didn't die. אמר amar, רב Rav אלעזר במחלוקת שנויה
*amar Rav Elazar bemachloket shenuya* of Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon, you
know what, you're right, Rabbi Meir actually would disagree in the first
case when one said dead and the other said didn't dead, died.
And the first part of the Mishnah which says you split it,
that's Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon. But אין הכי נמי *ein hachi
nami*, in the same way Rabbi Meir says died and killed neutralize,
he would say died and didn't die neutralize. ורבי יוחנן אמר amar,
אפילו תימא רבי מאיר *veRabbi Yochanan amar afilu teima Rabbi Meir*. No,
he reads the Mishnah more simply. Rabbi Meir says there's a difference
between died and killed as opposed to died and didn't die. בהא
אפילו רבי מאיר מודה *beha afilu Rabbi Meir modeh*. In the case
of died and didn't die, Rabbi Meir would agree that they do
not neutralize. Why? דכל לא מת בעדות אשה לאו הכא היא *dechol
lo meit be'edut isha lav hacha hi*. Any claim he's not dead
doesn't count. It's worthless. Now you cannot read that as completely as
categorically because we just, the end of the Mishnah says one says
dead, one says didn't dead, they neutralize, right? So it's not that
any claim of didn't die is ignored, right? One against one, they
do neutralize. It means any claim of the co-wife that he didn't
die is rejected. Okay, got that? Because obviously if you don't believe
a co-wife to say he's dead for the other wife, you also
don't believe a co-wife to say he's not dead for the other
wife. Any claim of the co-wife is completely ignored. But that's a
claim of he didn't die. A claim that he died for herself
is accepted. And once each wife's testimony is accepted for herself and
they are sort of accepted into testimony, but then they're saying different
things, dead and killed, that's where Rabbi Meir says they contradict. Okay,
לאו הכא היא תנן *lav hacha hi tnan*. So we learn in
the Mishnah, עד אומר מת ועד אומר לא מת אשה אומרת מת
ואשה אומרת לא מת *ed omer meit ve'ed omer lo meit isha
omeret meit ve'isha omeret lo meit*. הרי זו לא תינשא *harei zu
lo tinasei*. So it says that they can't get married, they do
neutralize. בשלמא לרבי אלעזר סתמא כרבי מאיר *bishlama leRabbi Elazar stama keRabbi
Meir*. So according to Rabbi Elazar it makes sense because the Gemara
is assuming when it says one woman says dead, one says not
dead, it includes the case of co-wife. Why we should assume it
includes the case of co-wife I have no idea. So it says,
so you know, so why is this that they neutralize? So according
to Rabbi Elazar this is like Rabbi Meir that says that they
would neutralize even by dead and didn't die. אלא לרבי יוחנן קשיא
*ella leRabbi Yochanan kashya*. According to Rabbi Yochanan why would the testimony
of two co-wives neutralize one another if it's died and didn't die?
If even Rabbi Meir agrees that that case is okay. So the
Gemara says, I mean, קשיא *kashya*, you're right, that's difficult. All right,
that was a little bizarre because it read the end of the
Mishnah to be talking about co-wives. But the upshot of it is,
is that the co-wife is not believed for the other one to
say dead and therefore also not believed for the other one to
say that he didn't die. And that the statement is that even
Rabbi Meir would agree with that. Because then it's seen as maybe
specifically coming to hurt the other wife. You're saying died, you want
to remarry, I'm saying don't, didn't die. I'm coming to like you
know, תמות נפשי עם פלשתים *tamut nafshi im Plishtim* type of a
thing. So when a woman is coming to testify for the co-wife
that the husband is dead or isn't dead, either way it's rejected.
The interesting debate is when each wife says he died but in
different ways. And is that because each testimony is accepted for the
wives themselves but they're different testimonies, is that going to create problems
of neutralizing? That's the position of Rabbi Meir. All right, so now
we continue. So again what we've learned is one against one does
neutralize if it's before it's accepted in בית דין beit din, *Beit
Din*, after it's accepted in בית דין beit din *Beit Din* it
cannot be neutralized. One wife is not believed for the other co-wife.
And now we're learning not just to say that he's dead, but
even not believed to contradict and to say he did not die.
Next Mishnah. האשה שהלכה
היא ובעלה למדינת הים *ha'isha shehalcha hi uva'ala limdinat hayam*. A woman
went she and her husband to Hawaii. ובאה ואמרה *uva'a ve'amra*. That's
the technical definition of מדינת הים Medinas Hayam *medinat hayam*. ובאה ואמרה
מת בעלי
U-va'ah v'amrah met
ba'ali, *uva'a ve'amra meit ba'ali*.
And she came back and said my husband died. That's a classic
case, right? תינשא ותיטול כתובתה *tinasei vetitol
ketubata*. She can marry and collect her כתובה kesuvah *ketubah*. Classic case.
וצרתה אסורה
*vetzarata asura*.
The co-wife not. That's what we said. A woman's testimony is not
believed for the co-wife. Okay, הייתה בת ישראל לכהן תאכל בתרומה *hayeta
bat Yisrael lechohen tochal bitruma*. דברי רבי טרפון divrei Rabbi Tarfon. *divrei
Rabbi Tarfon*. Now the co-wife, she can't remarry. Does she have to
be concerned that maybe the guy is dead? Right, if we don't
allow her to accept the testimony and remarry, but is it enough
to make a doubt? What would the doubt do? The doubt would
say, if she was married, let's say she was married to a
כהן Kohen. *kohen*, would we
allow her
to... continue to eat תרומה. Terumah. Yeah, we have to be consistent.
We totally reject the testimony for the co-wife. רבי עקיבא אומר אין
זו דרך מוציאה מידי עבירה. Rabbi Akiva Omer Ein Zo Derech Motziah
MiYedei Aveirah.
This is not going to protect her from sinning עד שתהא אסורה
להינשא ואסורה מלאכול בתרומה. ad she'tehei asura l'hinasei v'asura m'le'echol b'Terumah. You
have to be, say, definitely rejecting the testimony, we're doubtful rejecting the
testimony, so you have to be safe on both sides. Don't get
remarried, but also maybe the guy did die so don't go ahead
and don't eat תרומה. Terumah Okay, much more מחמיר machmir position by
because if you take a ספק safek stance then obviously you are
going to have to play it safe.
Now, אמרה מת. amra meis.
So let's say she says that he dies, hold on a second...
okay,
אמרה מת בעלי ואחר
כך מת חמי.
amra meis ba'ali v'achar
kach meis chami.
Now, we had this case before, a woman comes back and she
says my husband died and then my father-in-law died. Okay, we were
all vacationing, my husband died and then my father-in-law. Now, a woman
is not normally believed to testify for her חמותה, chamota, her mother-in-law,
you will remember, but here she is saying that at the time
my father-in-law died he was no longer my father-in-law, my husband died
first. So if you accept her testimony that the husband died, then
you should also believe her that say her father-in-law died because he's
no longer the father-in-law. Okay, so and a woman is believed to
testify for her ex-mother-in-law. Let's say we knew her husband died, right?
Let's say there was witnesses that her husband died, then she could
testify about her mother-in-law, about her father-in-law, her ex-father-in-law. So here she's
doing it based on her own testimony. אמרה מת בעלי ואחר כך
מת חמי תינשא ותיטול כתובתה. amra meis ba'ali v'achar kach meis chami
tinasei v'titol kesuvata. She can collect her כתובה kesuvah. וחמותה אסורה, v'chamota
asura, but no, we do not accept the testimony for the mother-in-law
in this case because since it's all based on her testimony, we're
concerned that she's making the whole thing up just to get back
at her mother-in-law. Okay, so her mother-in-law, the testimony is still rejected
for the mother-in-law. היתה בת ישראל לכהן תאכל בתרומה. haysa bas Yisrael
l'Kohen tochal b'Terumah. And therefore the mother-in-law assumes that her husband is
definitely alive and can continue to eat תרומה Terumah. if she was
married to a כהן. Kohen, דברי רבי טרפון. divrei Rabbi Tarfon. רבי
עקיבא אומר אין זו דרך מוציאה מידי עבירה, Rabbi Akiva Omer Ein
Zo Derech Motziah MiYedei Aveirah, same point.
This does not protect her from sinning, the mother-in-law, עד שתהא אסורה
להינשא ואסורה מלאכול בתרומה. ad she'tehei asura l'hinasei v'asura m'le'echol b'Terumah. She
can't remarry and she can't eat תרומה. Terumah. So it winds up
that you could, you could make life difficult for your mother-in-law anyway,
right? If she's married to a כהן, kohen, you testify that the
husband is dead and then at least you stop her from eating
תרומה. Terumah. Yes?
In the first case it seems a bit unfair, I mean that
the co-wife is put in this position because it could be that
the wife who went on the trip has no animosity towards the
co-wife, she just came back and reported it, and she's allowed to
be remarried and get a כתובה.
kesuvah, Right, you're right, it's difficult. Like on the one hand, that's
the flip side of what I was saying, like it could be
that the woman is lying and she says okay I'll lie even
if it won't ruin her in terms of her marrying a guy
and having committed adultery or whatever the case was, it'll ruin her
because she won't be able to eat תרומה. Terumah Right, so that's
creates more of an incentive for her to lie. But your point
is, what about the flip case that she's telling the truth? What's
this poor co-wife supposed to do? You know, either believe my co-wife
and let me remarry, or don't believe her. But why because... yeah,
so that's, I understand.
I mean because we're allowing the original one who came back to
remarry, to have all the privileges.
Exactly, exactly. You really do understand רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon's position, you
know, you really do. So, look, sometimes life is unfair, but it's
still... but if we're making the rules here, you know, you understand
the attraction of רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon's position.
One question: Surely as you said once the husband dies then the
relationship with the mother-in-law or father-in-law is no longer fraught, but does
it only really apply to the idea that it's economic? Because if
it's the...
yeah,
you could have lingering animosity. Yeah, so Michael sort of also asked
the other day, you know, we don't go ahead and ask like
before we accept your testimony, oh I know that you guys were
sworn enemies or something like that, although in there is a הלכה
halacha in עדות eidus of שונא. sonei. So there is a category
of like a real enemy. But anyway, but we don't normally say
like, I know you guys had animosity, I know there were things
between the two of you, right? We create formal categories. So, and
sometimes those formal categories are too broad, like I get along great
with my mother-in-law, right? And sometimes they're too narrow, like even though
she's my ex-mother-in-law, I still hate her, right? So but you know,
for a legal system you need some formal categories. But yes, yeah.
I just find myself siding with
רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. Okay, you like the testimony to be believed
for the co-wife? Yeah, I understand.
And she's believed, but I'm saying she's allowed to remarry and get
a כתובה, kesubah? the first wife. Right. So why shouldn't the second
wife be allowed to do that also, not just a question of
eating תרומה or not.
Right.
Right. Right, so again, that was a concern that the first wife
is making it up and she's just trying—look, part of the whole—you
understand, it is frustrating. Look, part of the whole thing also is
right that it's like the rabbis are like they created this whole
amazing category of believing people that normally the testimony would be thrown
out. And then they felt they had to put certain limits on
it, you know, to be responsible about it. But yeah, I do
understand that it would be very frustrating, you know, for somebody who
would be caught in this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: וצריכה. u'tzricha. You need both cases about the split, about sort
of the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon by the co-wife and the debate by the mother-in-law. דאי איתמר
בהך קמייתא, De'itmar behach kamayta, if it had just said the co-wife,
בהך קאמר רבי טרפון behach ka'amar Rabbi Tarfon משום דצרה דגופא, mishum
ditzara degufa, that is because Rabbi Tarfon would say that there you
sort of completely reject the, you know, the testimony of the co-wife
because, you know, the animosity grows up because they're like they, you
know, their very person is being affected because, you know, the co-wife
basically, it's like my husband sleeps with you and not with me,
you know, and there's obviously that much more personal type of animosity.
And therefore you should completely reject the testimony of one wife for
the other. Okay? אבל חמותה, Aval chamota, but the mother-in-law, דצרה מילי
דעלמא, ditzara milei de'alma, right, what did the—why did the גמרא Gemara
say that you don't believe a woman to testify about her mother-in-law?
Right? Because, because she says, oh, I don't like her, my mother-in-law
tells, you know, badmouths me to my husband. All right? So that's
not as personal as the type of jealousy and animosity that grows
up between the co-wives. So therefore, אימא מודי ליה לרבי עקיבא, eima
modi lei leRabbi Akiva, maybe he'd agree to Rabbi Akiva that we
can't completely reject the testimony, we have to treat it as a
ספק. safek. ואי איתמר בהא, Ve'itmar beha, if it had just said
the second case about the mother-in-law, בהא קאמר רבי עקיבא, beha ka'amar
Rabbi Akiva, that's where Rabbi Akiva says we can—it's only doubtful whether
we reject it or not and we have to play it safe.
אבל בהך בעיתא דצרה, Aval behach bayata ditzara, by the co-wife, אימא
מודי ליה לרבי טרפון, eima modi lei leRabbi Tarfon, maybe he would
agree that we completely reject it, there's so much animosity we completely
reject it. צריכא, Tzricha, so you need both cases. אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הלכה כרבי טרפון. halacha keRabbi
Tarfon. We rule like Rabbi Tarfon, which, so now you should be
feeling at least a little relieved, David. Okay? It's not, it's not
that we allow both wives to marry, but at least she doesn't
have to suffer in this middle state. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אף
אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tanina, we taught similarly, נתנה לי
בן במדינת הים. nitna li ben bimdinat hayam. We're about to read
this משנה. mishnah. A woman comes back and testifies and she says
a child was born to me when we were overseas, me and
my husband. מת בני ואחר כך בעלי, Met beni ve'achar kach ba'ali,
my son died and then my husband died, נאמנת. ne'emenet. She's believed,
which basically means, right, she, when she left we thought she'd be
חייבת ביבום, chayavet beyibum, there was no child. She said there was
her child and then he died, so she basically neutralized the effect
of her testimony. So then she's believed and she's believed to the
point that we even allow יבום yibum now. בעלי ואחר כך בני,
Ba'ali ve'achar kach beni, if she says my husband died and then
my son, so basically she left and we thought that she would
be obligated in יבום yibum if the husband died. Now she's coming
back and saying actually I had a child and he died after
my husband, so she's trying to testify that she's not obligated in
יבום yibum and changing her previous status. So in that case אינה
נאמנת, eina ne'emenet, she's not believed, וחוששין לדבריה, vechoshishin lidvareha, but you
still have to play it safe. So she's not believed to get
out of יבום, yibum, but because it might be true, you don't
allow her to do יבום, yibum, right? Because she said I had
a son when my husband died. So therefore how do you play
it safe? חולצת ולא מתייבמת. Choletzet velo mityabemet. And she just חליצה,
chalitzah, not יבום. yibum. Okay,
that's how you play it safe. Now what does that have anything
to do with our case? So the דיוק diyuk of the גמרא
Gemara is, and this seems like a pretty stretched דיוק, diyuk, הוא
דחוששים לדבריה. hu dechoshshim lidvareha. It's חוששים לדבריה choshshim lidvareha with the
specific point of her words. So when she says this type of
a testimony, then we have to play it safe because she's saying
it about herself. הא לדברי צרה, Ha lidvrei tzara, but when she—somebody,
a woman is testifying vis-a-vis her co-wife, אין חוששין, ein chosheshin, you're
not concerned. So somehow it makes a big דיוק, diyuk, it doesn't
just say חוששין, choshshim, it says חוששים לדבריה. choshshim lidvareha. When she's
testifying about herself, we could be in a state where we don't
believe it but we play it safe, but when it's about her
co-wife we're not going to believe it at all. שמע מינה, Shma
mina, and that seems the גמרא Gemara seems satisfied. So at least
the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara is that we don't make the
co-wife live in this very conflicted, you know, nebulous space, right? If
we're not going to accept the testimony, we completely reject it and
she can go on living her life as she would have. All
right. Next משנה. mishnah. Now we get to be a little bit
of a digression because of this debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. Let's take a look. קידש אחת מחמש
נשים. Kidesh achat michamesh nashim.
A man married one of five women. ואינו יודע איזו קידש. Ve'eino
yodeia eizo kidesh.
He doesn't know which one he married. Now remember of course this
does not mean חופה chuppah and נישואין nissu'in that they started living
together, it could have been, you know, five years before they were
going to actually start to live together and he just gave כסף
קידושין kesef kiddushin and it also could have been an arranged marriage.
For all we know it could have been טביה's Tevye five daughters,
so he gave כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin to טביה Tevye and he
forgot which one did he—did he have intent to מקדש? mekadesh? Okay,
so it's not an impossible situation. In those, given the realities of
those times. So what does he do? כל אחת אומרת אותי קידש.
kol achas omeres oti kidesh. And everyone says, I'm the one who
he married. So נותן גט לכל אחת ואחת, nosein get le-chol achas
ve-achas, he has to give a get to each one because if
he doesn't want to be married to all five, or if they're
all sisters he can't, in my scenario. Anyway, so he can't go
ahead and live with any one of them, might not be his
wife, and he doesn't want to be married to all five. So
he has to give a get to all of them. And what
does he do about the payment of the כתובה? kesubah ומניח כתובה
ביניהם ומסתלק. u-maniach kesubah beneihem u-mistalek.
So he just says here, here's the כתובה kesubah money, you guys
fight it out, okay? Because it's a doubtful obligation to,
he knows he's obligated to one of these people, but he doesn't
know which one.
So it gets to interesting questions of המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
me-chavero alav ha-re'ayah. Now by the way, if you think about it
in those terms, and that is a way the גמרא Gemara elsewhere
sort of thinks about it, each particular woman comes up to him
and says, you owe me $100. And he says, I don't know,
maybe I do, maybe I don't. So what do we say about
a ודאי vadai against a ספק safek in a case where one
guy is מוחזק? muchzak? He has the money in his property. Is
it like המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה hamotzi me-chavero alav ha-re'ayah if the
other one is saying you still definitely owe me? And here we
know, now there's a case
where you say, I lent you $100 and I say I don't
know. I lent you $100 and I say I don't know. That's
one scenario. There's another scenario where basically you say,
I know I lent you $100, I don't know if I paid
you back. In that case, obviously it's much more likely that I'd
have to pay it out, because I'm conceding to the debt. This
is a case where it's in a middle situation. I know I
owe one of you that money, but as to you, the particular
one that's coming to me, I don't know if it's you that
I ever owed the money. I know I owed it to maybe
one of you. So it's an interesting type of way to frame
the issue as המוציא מחבירו. hamotzi me-chavero. One is making a definite
claim, the other's saying I don't know. Is that enough to extract
the money? And here's the case where I know there's an obligation,
but I don't know that it was to you. Okay, so this
is the issue.
So דברי רבי טרפון. divrei Rabbi Tarfon. Rabbi Tarfon says you just
give them the $100 and let them fight it out, okay? You
don't have to pay each one. רבי עקיבא אומר אין זו דרך
מוציא מידי עבירה. Rabbi Akiva omer ein zo derech motzi mi-yedei aveirah.
This does not save you from a sin, the exact same language
we had before, עד שיתן גט וכתובה לכל אחת ואחת. ad she-yitein
get ve-kesubah le-chol achas ve-achas. You have to pay each one. Now
the interesting question is with Rabbi Akiva, is that are you really
דיני ממונות dinei mamonos obligated? Would a court demand that you do
this? If you refuse and you say, I don't care, when I
come up to שמים shamayim I'll pay for it. Are you going
to say that like דיני ממונות dinei mamonos I have a legal
obligation to pay each one? It's not clear, right? אין זו דרך
מוציא מידי עבירה ein zo derech motzi mi-yedei aveirah might be Rabbi
Akiva saying you have a moral obligation to pay each one, and
we're going to try to get you to do it. We're going
to tell you you have to do it. But if you're asking
technically legally, maybe the answer is no. And that's a fascinating area
of הלכה halacha where there's a sense of a clearly identified moral
obligation without it technically like that the court actually articulates, but without
it actually being a legal obligation. Okay, like for example, there's a
גמרא Gemara that says, let's say you put poison in front of
your friend's cow and he eats it and he dies. Okay, so
technically you're exempt. It's a גרמא, gerama, indirect. Okay, but the גמרא
Gemara says you might be פטור בדיני אדם patur bi-dinei adam but
you're חייב בדיני שמים, chayav bi-dinei shamayim, right, חייב בדיני שמים. chayav
bi-dinei shamayim. So what does that mean? It means that until I
pay the guy the money, somehow I have this debt hanging over
my head which the court might not actually enforce, but on the
other hand, it's a specific concrete sort of moral obligation to pay
a debt. So it's not clear whether Rabbi Akiva is talking in
strictly legal terms here. Yes.
Wait, so you're treating the כתובה kesubah as a contractual debt, in
other words, when they did the קידושין kiddushin there was a contract?
Yes, yes. It was because, good question, because a כתובה kesuba isn't
written until the נישואין, nisuin, but it is imposed by the Rabbis
already from the time of קידושין, kiddushin, so it's an automatic obligation,
an implicit, yes, there's a question, is it תקנת חכמים takanas chachamim
or is it a contract, but either way it's done implicitly, not
through anything written. Okay, so here's another similar case. גזל אחד מחמשה.
gezel echad mi-chamishah.
A person stole from five people ואיני יודע מאיזה גזל. ve-eini yodeia
mi-eizeh gazal. Don't know which one you stole from. כל אחד אומר
אותי גזל. kol echad omer oti gazal. You stole from me. מניח
גזילה ביניהם ומסתלק maniach gezeilah beneihem u-mistalek דברי רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon
Rabbi Tarfon says here you guys, here's the thing, you fight it
out. רבי עקיבא אומר אין זו דרך מוציא מידי עבירה Rabbi Akiva
omer ein zo derech motzi mi-yedei aveirah עד שישלם לכל אחד ואחד.
ad she-yeshaleim le-chol achas ve-achas. This does not save you from sin,
you have to pay each one. Now the obvious difference between the
two cases, which the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to immediately,
is that case number one is you didn't do anything that was
morally wrong and therefore it makes more sense that you don't have
a, that your obligation is not as heightened, whereas in the second
case where you actually did something morally and halachically wrong, you stole,
that might create a greater obligation, whether moral or legal obligation, but
a greater obligation to rectify the situation fully. Okay, and So it
seems like from our משנה Mishna that they argue in both cases,
that whether it’s a lower or a higher moral obligation, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says in both cases you’re חייב chayav and רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon says in neither case you’re חייב. chayav. But the גמרא
Gemara is going to sort of say that maybe they were only
debating one set of those questions and not the other. So let’s
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. קידש
קתני, Kidesh katani, it speaks about doing קידושין, kidushin, בעל לא קתני,
ba’al lo katani, but not with having had sex yet with one
of the women and it seems like we’re not talking just about
ביאת נישואין, bi’as nisuein, but actually like if it’s a bit of
a ביאת קידושין, bi’as kidushin, okay? So an act of just giving
כסף קידושין kesef kidushin does not create any particular, you know, unique...
there was no violation that should engender some type of a special
moral obligation, okay. גזל קתני, Gazal katani, but on the other hand
the second case spoke about stealing. לקח לא קתני, Lakach lo katani,
not like I purchased this object from one of you and I
don’t remember who I purchased it from. Okay, so the second case
is a case that there was some real violation. So מני מתניתין,
mani masnisin, who is our משנה Mishna going like? לא תנא קמא
ולא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Lo tanna kamma v’lo Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar, not the תנא קמא tanna kamma of a ברייתא braisa we’ll
quote and not רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. There’s
really not a תנא קמא, tanna kamma, there’s just an implicit תנא
קמא. tanna kamma. דתניא, Detania, we taught in a ברייתא: braisa: רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אומר: Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer: לא נחלקו רבי
טרפון ורבי עקיבא על שקידש אחת מחמישה נשים ואינו יודע איזה קידש,
Lo necheleku Rabbi Tarfon v’Rabbi Akiva al she-kidesh achas m-chamesha nashim v’eino
yodeia eizu kidesh, שמניח כתובה ביניהם ומסתלק. she-maniach kesuba beineihen u-mistalek. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon did not disagree in
a case of just marrying one of five women, there there’s no
special moral obligation and therefore he just gives the כתובה kesuba money
and they fight it out. Even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would agree
to that. על מה נחלקו? Al mah necheleku? על שבעל. Al she-ba’al.
The debate was when he did the קידושין kidushin through an act
of sex, okay? You’re not supposed to do קידושי ביאה kidushei bi’ah
although it works, and one could say that having actually had sex
with a woman, forget whether the rabbis like קידושי ביאה kidushei bi’ah
or not, sort of create particular obligation to that woman. You don’t
know who she is, but if you now have not just, you
know, you could say if you gave her קידושין kidushin and now
you give her a גט get you’ve made her a גרושה grusha
that hurts her for a כהן, Kohen, but certainly if you’ve had
sex with this woman and now you’re not going to continue to
be married to her and you’re going to just basically extract yourself
from the situation, you might have a unique obligation to make sure
that she gets her כתובה kesuba money, and that you might have
to pay every single one to make sure that the one you’ve
had sex with is getting her כתובה kesuba money. Okay. So that’s
not...
that’s not נישואין. nisuein. That’s קידושי ביאה, kidushei bi’ah, correct. Okay. Even
doing נישואין nisuein you’d have
sex again, but the point is the sex there might have been
in the father’s house and this would be the sex in your
house, you know, and so נישואין nisuein is not just sex, it’s
also sex in the context of setting up house.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: על מה נחלקו? Al mah necheleku?
על שבעל. Al she-ba’al. רבי טרפון אומר: Rabbi Tarfon omer: שמניח כתובה
ביניהם ומסתלק. maniach kesuba beineihen u-mistalek. Even there רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
says give the כתובה kesuba money and just extract yourself. רבי עקיבא
אומר: Rabbi Akiva omer: עד שישלם כתובה לכל אחת ואחת. ad she-yeshaleim
kesuba l’chol achas v’achas. No, that creates a special responsibility and you
have to make sure you’re making the other person, you’re fully satisfying
your obligations to the other person and you have to pay the
כתובה money to each one. Similarly, לא נחלקו רבי טרפון ורבי עקיבא
על שלקח מחמישה בני אדם ואינו יודע מאיזה מהם לקח, lo necheleku
Rabbi Tarfon v’Rabbi Akiva al she-lakach mi-chamisha benei adam v’eino yodeia me-eizeh
meihen lakach, they’re not debating that you took from one of five
storekeepers and you don’t remember which one you bought it from, שמניח
דמי מקח ביניהם ומסתלק. she-maniach dmei mekach beineihen u-mistalek. You put the
money between them and let them fight it out, because, you know,
you don’t know and you don’t have a special responsibility in that
case. על מה נחלקו? Al mah necheleku? לא נחלקו אלא שגזל מחמישה,
Lo necheleku ela she-gazal mi-chamisha, only when you stole. שאמר רבי טרפון:
She-amar Rabbi Tarfon: מניח גזילה ביניהם ומסתלק, maniach gezeila beineihen u-mistalek, you
just put the stolen object and you walk away. ורבי עקיבא אומר:
V’Rabbi Akiva omer: עד שישלם גזילה לכל אחת ואחת. ad she-yeshaleim gezeila
l’chol achas v’achas. No, you have to go ahead because you stole
from one of them, you better make sure that you have restored
the object to the person you stole to and therefore you have
to give it to every single one, you have to pay back
every single one. So that’s a very reasonable position that that’s where
creates the special obligation that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is talking about.
So our משנה Mishna is obviously not רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar, because our משנה Mishna has them debating even the
case of קידש kidesh without בעל, ba’al, right, even a case of
a lesser obligation. So it’s not רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar. And then the גמרא Gemara says like this: מדקאמר רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר, Mid-ka’amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, since רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says בקידש ולקח לא פליגי, b’kidesh v’lakach
lo pleigi, that they’re not debating the case of קידש kidesh and
לקח, lakach, of just קידושין kidushin and just purchase, so מכלל דתנא
קמא סבר פליגי, mikhlal d’tanna kamma savar pleigi, presumably he’s arguing with
another approach that thinks that the debate was in those scenarios of
simple קידושין kidushin and simple purchase. Okay. Now מני, mani, if that’s
true, who is our משנה? Mishna? אי תנא קמא, I tanna kamma,
if it’s the תנא קמא tanna kamma who says that they’re debating
the cases of not a heightened moral obligation but a simple case
of קידש kidesh and לקח, lakach, so לתני קידש ולקח. lisni kidesh
v’lakach. Tell me those cases, right, tell me not just the קידש
kidesh case but also the לקח, lakach, because our משנה Mishna had
one of each. The case of קידש kidesh which was not a
heightened obligation and the case
of... if
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, tell
us the two cases of the heightened obligation, בעל וגזל. ba’al v’gazal.
Now of course the simple point could be maybe the תנא קמא
tanna kamma holds they argue both cases, right, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says you have the obligation even in the lesser scenario, right, even
in the case of קידש, kidesh, and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says
you don’t have the obligation even in the greater scenario, even in
the case
of גזל. gazal. But for some reason the גמרא Gemara doesn't say
that. That would seem the easiest approach, that the assumption of the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is that they argue across the board. The
גמרא Gemara wants to say they either argue only in the lesser
case or only in the greater case. So who's our משנה Mishnah
going like? So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם Le-olam רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, really it's רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar that says that they're arguing in the heightened case,
the case of heightened obligation, ומאי קידש קידש בביאה, U-mai kiddesh? Kiddesh
be-biah, and when it says קידש, kiddesh, it means the case of
ביאה, biah, it means the case of sex. So our case is
that רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position that you have to make good
with everyone is only in the case of a special heightened obligation,
of the case of sex or, what do you call it, or
the case of גזל. Gazal. But in the other cases, even רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would admit you have no special responsibility.
ומאי תנא קידש? U-mai tanna kiddesh? And why does it have to
do the two cases of קידש kiddesh and the case of גזל?
Gazal? קידש kiddesh is to tell you the strength of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva because that might be a case where your responsibility is
a little less even if it came through an act of sex.
דאף על גב דאיסור דרבנן, De-af al gav de-issur d'Rabbanan, even though
having קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah is only an איסור דרבנן, issur d'Rabbanan,
so you might think, oh, he didn't do an איסור
דאורייתא, issur d'Oraita, nevertheless עבד עבד, avad avad, קניס kanis רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva fines him and demands that he pay. Now of course
from an איסור issur standpoint, קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah is less bad
than גזילה. gzeilah. But from a how you impacted the other person,
I mean let's first on the other גזילה gzeilah also a person
could really feel violated, okay? But anyway, on a personal level it
might be different. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara says that even within
the context of the heightened obligation cases, there's still a gradation, that
קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah is less serious than גזל. Gazal. So in
that case, maybe that's why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, that's a
חידוש chiddush for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that even in the קידושי
ביאה kiddushei biah he makes the guy pay. תנא גזל Tanna Gazal
and had the case of stealing, להודיע כוחו דרבי טרפון, le-hodi'a kocho
de-Rabbi Tarfon, that even in that case where דאף על גב דאיסור
דאורייתא עבד, de-af al gav de-issur d'Oraita avad, even though the guy
did an איסור דאורייתא issur d'Oraita of גזילה gzeilah and also there
was an aspect of violation, nevertheless
לא קניס lo kanis רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon does not make the
guy pay. Okay, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva makes him pay, but
according to the way the גמרא Gemara concluded within רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar only when there's a heightened obligation, there's
some real violation that was done, and even in those cases רבי
טרפון does not. What's worth pointing out is the word that the
גמרא Gemara introduced at the very end was קניס, קנס, kanis, knas,
fine. And that gets to my question, which is, is רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva saying that you are literally, you know, דיני ממונות dinei
mamonot legally mandated to pay every single one? And it sounds like
the גמרא Gemara saying no, but rather than framing it as he
wants you, he's sort of morally mandating you to pay—what does morally
mandating me to pay mean? I say I don't want to do
it. You have to do it. Legally no, but you have to.
So how does that translate? So the גמרא Gemara translates it as
a קנס. knas. We're going to force you by a fine and
not say that strictly דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, but we're going to
create a, we're going to mandate you in terms of a fine
to pay even if it's not a strict דיני ממונות dinei mamonot
obligation. Yes David.
If the clarification is not necessarily a violation,
I mean—it
is because the rabbis said that they don't want people to do
קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah. So it actually there is an איסור דרבנן
issur d'Rabbanan to do קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah.
I meant a violation of the woman, in
terms of stealing, the act of stealing is violation. The act of
sex was not violation at the time. Now that the guy's walking
away and whatever, now she might feel at least you know used
or violated, whatever, it's not the same thing as at the time
of the event, right, absolutely. Okay, so next, now let's find—last משנה
Mishnah of the second to last פרק. Perek. האישה שהלכה היא ובעלה
למדינת הים, Ha-isha she-halcha hi u-ba'alah limdinat ha-yam,
so we've sort of quoted sections of this משנה Mishnah before, a
woman who she and her husband went to Hawaii. ובנה עמהם, U-vnah
imahem, it's always Hawaii, ובנה עמהם, u-vnah imahem, and they took their
son with them, so when she left we assume that she would
not be obligated in ייבום Yibum were her husband to die, okay?
ובאה ואמרה מת בעלי, she says her husband died, which we believe
her. ואחר כך מת בני, V'achar kach met bni, and then my
son died, נאמנת, ne'emenet, she's believed because she's basically, she's not believed
about the son because a woman doesn't have any special believability about
the son, it's the believability about the husband. So she believes the
husband died, and anyway we assume she's not obligated in ייבום, Yibum,
so fine. Now מת בני ואחר כך מת בעלי, Met bni v'achar
kach met ba'ali, let's say she says my son died first, which
is basically saying I'm obligated in ייבום. Yibum. Now but it's not
only obligated, I'm also allowed in ייבום, Yibum, I can go and
marry my brother-in-law. Okay, now in that case אינה נאמנת, eina ne'emenet,
she's not believed, because again she has no special believability about her
son, so she's not believed to change her status and to now
say that there's a מצווה mitzvah of ייבום Yibum and to allow
the, her to live with her brother-in-law. That's not accepted. וחוששין לדבריה,
V'chosheshin lidvareiha, but you have to play it safe, okay, because she's
saying that she's also implicitly saying she's not allowed to marry another
man until she gets חליצה. chalitzah. חולצת ולא מתייבמת, Choletzet v'lo mityabemet,
so you put the stringencies on her, you demand חליצה chalitzah but
you do not allow for ייבום. Yibum. That's scenario one. Now let's
say she says the following: ניתן לי יבם במדינת הים, Nitan li
yabam b'medinat ha-yam,
when I was over in Hawaii I was there with my husband
and my mother-in-law and you know my in-laws and they had a
son... son, meaning my in-laws had a son. I got a new,
I got a new brother-in-law over in Hawaii. Okay, so she is
testifying to the fact she left, there was no brother, we thought
that she would never be obligated in ייבום, yibbum, she's testifying, she's
now testifying to the fact that there is a ייבום yibbum obligation.
Again, she has no special believability, but based on her words, that's
what happened. ניתן לי יבם במדינת הים. nittan li yavam bimdinas hayam.
I had a brother-in-law. I'm sorry, did I skip a line? I
skipped, I skipped to the second case. ניתן לי בן במדינת הים.
nittan li ben bimdinas hayam. No,
did we do that? No, we did not. I'm sorry. So back,
I'm sorry, I did skip. So, by the asterisk, okay. ניתן לי
בן במדינת הים. nittan li ben bimdinas hayam. I skipped, excuse me.
She left without any kids. So when she left, we assumed she
would be obligated in ייבום, yibbum, okay? And then she says, "When
I was in מדינת הים Medinas Hayam, I had a kid," ואמרה
מת בני ואחר כך מת בעלי. v'amrah meis beni v'achar kach meis
ba'ali. And then he died before my, and then my husband died.
So in that case, basically she's neutralized her own statement, right? And
anyway, we assumed when she left, she'd be obligated in ייבום. yibbum.
So in that case, נאמנת, ne'emenes, she's believed. Because really the only
thing she's believed about is about her husband, and the two statements
about the son are just completely ignored. Now let's say she says,
מת בעלי ואחר כך מת בני. meis ba'ali v'achar kach meis beni.
She says, "My husband died and then my son died." So she
left with no son. She came back and she said, "I actually
had a son and he died after my husband died." So she's
basically trying to say, "I left thinking, you know, with a status
that I'd be obligated in ייבום. yibbum. I'm telling you I'm not
obligated in ייבום." yibbum. In that case, she's not believed. She has
again, her believability is only in terms of her husband. In that
case, אינה נאמנת, einah ne'emenes, she's not believed, but וחוששין לדבריה. v'choshishin
lidvareha. Since now she's telling us she's exempt from ייבום, yibbum, we
have to at least be concerned to not allow ייבום, yibbum, to
demand חליצה, chalitzah, right? Because since she's saying she's totally exempt, but
so we have to play it safe. And what do we say?
חולצת ולא מתייבמת. choletzes v'lo misyabemes. She does חליצה chalitzah and not
ייבום yibbum because she's saying that she is exempt, we cannot allow
ייבום, yibbum, but we have to, but we're still going to demand
חליצה. chalitzah. Now, ניתן לי יבם, nittan li yavam, this is what
I had skipped to. ניתן לי יבם במדינת הים. nittan li yavam
bimdinas hayam. Let's say she says a brother-in-law was born to me
before, my husband had no brothers. ואמרה מת בעלי ואחר כך מת
יבמי. v'amrah meis ba'ali v'achar kach meis yabmi. So first she left,
we would have thought no ייבום yibbum obligation. Then she says a
brother was born in מדינת הים, okay? And then she says, ניתן
לי יבם במדינת הים, nittan li yavam bimdinas hayam, ואמרה מת בעלי
ואחר כך מת יבמי. v'amrah meis ba'ali v'achar kach meis yabmi. So
first my husband died and then my brother-in-law died. או יבמי ואחר
כך בעלי, o yabmi v'achar kach ba'ali, my brother-in-law then my husband.
Really doesn't matter the order, right? She basically is saying, "I had
a brother-in-law and then he died. Right now there's no brother-in-law, so
it doesn't matter when he died." נאמנת, ne'emenes, she's believed, because she
basically just completely neutralized her statement. I had a brother-in-law and then
he died. Good. Okay. הלכה היא ובעלה ויבמה למדינת הים. halchah hi
u'ba'alah v'yavamah limdinas hayam. She, her husband, and her brother-in-law all went
to Hawaii.
We know she has a brother-in-law. We know she'd be obligated in
ייבום. yibbum. And then she said, מת בעלי ואחר כך יבמי, meis
ba'ali v'achar kach yabmi, או יבמי ואחר כך בעלי. o yabmi v'achar
kach ba'ali. Again, doesn't matter what, when the brother-in-law died. She's basically
saying he's dead now and I'm not obligated in ייבום. yibbum. אינה
נאמנת. einah ne'emenes. She's not believed, because she basically is coming to
change her status. Now, here's the problem though: there's no brother-in-law around.
If the brother-in-law were around, she wouldn't be able to say testify
that he's dead, okay? So she is basically, we still assume there's
a brother-in-law and we're not going to let her remarry until that
brother-in-law shows up. Pretty difficult, right? Situation: goes with the brother-in-law, comes
by and says, she's not believed that he died, she's only believed
about her husband, not about her brother-in-law, but there's no brother-in-law to
do ייבום yibbum or חליצה, chalitzah, so she's pretty stuck, okay?
אינה נאמנת. einah ne'emenes. שאין אשה נאמנת לומר, she'ein ishah ne'emenes lomar,
because a woman is not believed to say מת יבמי, meis yabmi,
my brother-in-law died, שתנשא, she'tinasei, so that she should get married. She
has no believability about anybody other than her
husband. ולא מתה אחותה, v'lo meisah achosah, or here's another case. Let's
say she comes back and she reports, "Yeah, Reuven was married to
my sister and my sister died, and now I want to be
Reuven's wife." שתכנס לביתו. she'tikaneis l'veiso. Again, so this whole special rabbinic
institution of believing testimony of one witness and of the wife or
whatever is only about allowing a woman to remarry, not about creating
other changes of status. Similarly, ואין האיש נאמן לומר מת אחי שיבם
את אשתו. v'ein ha'ish ne'eman lomar meis achi she'yiyabem es ishto. A
man cannot come say my brother died. If a guy comes back
and says my brother died, okay, basically what he's doing is he's
testifying to his sister-in-law that her husband died, right? So her sister-in-law
actually can believe that her husband died. That's a case of believing
that a husband died. But not to the point that would allow
him to do ייבום. yibbum. You understand? It's an interesting scenario. Somebody
comes back and says to his sister-in-law, "My brother, your husband, died."
So if there are children, she can believe it. It's testimony that
a guy died and she can remarry. But if there are no
children, she cannot believe it to do ייבום, yibbum, okay? Because maybe
he's just, that's מתיר matir an איסור, issur, right? It's מתיר matir
the prohibition of brother's wife. So in that case, ולא מתה אשתו
שישא אחותה. v'lo meisah ishto she'yisa achosah. He's also not believed to
say that If he's married to רחל Rachel to say רחל Rachel
died and now I want to marry לאה. Leah. Okay, so he's
basically the only איסור issur or status that a person is believed
about is to allow a woman to remarry, not about יבום yibum
issues, sister issues, none of these other issues.
Okay.
Why is there a difference between the husband and the wife?
Like why don't we accept testimony for
the יבם yavam just like you do the husband? Is she basically
in the same status?
Because she's basically- you mean once we're allowing her testimony to believe
in terms of the איסור issur of אשת איש, eshes ish, why
can't we allow her testimony to believe her in terms of freeing
her from an obligation of חליצה? chalitzah? Is that what you're sort
of saying?
No, I'm saying in the case where she's stuck because she can't
testify about the יבם. yavam. Right. Why isn't that the same as...
like why do we believe her in the first place about her
husband because she shouldn't be an עגונה?
agunah? Right. So there's another עגונה agunah situation. Right, so that's... again,
it sort of goes back to the other point. It's not like
every time there was an עגונה, agunah, we're going to create a
special נאמנות ne'emanus to get out of it, right? The rabbis sort
of saw a major category of a woman's husband died. And it's
similar to the question before. You know, and then they had to
say we can't be irresponsible about this, we gotta put some limits
on it. So certain people were not going to be believed, we're
not going to believe about other situations that are not about husband
dying. Right, you know, otherwise things would obviously get a little bit
out of hand. But yeah, I do understand that logically, you know,
there are problems that exactly get created because you're not believing. But
formally, we're only believing in cases about the husband dying and not
about other implications. And again, the irony is that you believe the
brother that his brother died and that the woman could marry if
there were no kids, but you don't believe him to allow him
to do יבום. yibum. I mean, he could do חליצה chalitzah and
then she could get married. Okay, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. בעי מיני רבא מרב נחמן. Ba'ei minei Rava mei-Rav Nachman.
רבא Rava asked רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: המזכה גט לאשתו, Ha-mezakeh get
l'ishto, this is not expected, a whole גט get case. And this,
as you could imagine, is going to be an interesting discussion. It's
somewhat relevant to some of the contemporary עגונה agunah issues. Except here
the point is that the man wants to give a גט get
and the woman isn't around to be found or whatever for some
reason isn't present. So המזכה גט לאשתו במקום יבם מהו?
Ha-mezakeh get l'ishto bimkom
yavam, mahu? So basically, a guy could divorce his wife against her
will, but let's say she's not around. So can the guy basically
say "I'm appointing you, David, a שליח shaliach for my wife, to
represent my wife, and here's a גט get for my wife"? Now,
I can give a גט get to my wife against her will,
but I can't make... normally you can only create an agent if
you're agreeing to make somebody your agent. My wife never made you
her agent. How can I make you my wife's agent? So the
principle would be though, if it would be something in somebody's benefit,
you could do that without their knowledge or consent. If I said,
"David, I want to give you my car, you know, to דוב
Dov there, can you represent דוב Dov and take the keys to
my car and take it for דוב Dov as a present?" So
that I could do even though דוב Dov never made him his
agent, because it's for דוב's Dov benefit. So I can... you can
be מזכה, mezakeh, you can take possession of the car, right, for
somebody else if it's to their benefit. Can you take possession of
a גט get for my wife, right, if it's for her benefit?
Well, what would be her benefit? We normally wouldn't assume it would
be a woman's benefit to be divorced. But let's say there's a
brother-in-law, okay? And let's say I hate the brother... she hates the
brother-in-law, that's known. Now still, the point is, but we're in a
happy marriage, God willing should live to 120, why would she want
to be divorced now? Because there might be- but let's assume maybe
it's a special case. Maybe it's a case that the guy's on
his deathbed or he's going out to war or some type of
a thing that he figures his wife would better off be divorced
and not have to worry about the brother-in-law. So he wants to
give a גט get to his wife to get around יבום, yibum,
but the wife isn't present. So that's the question. Excuse
me. Okay. המזכה גט לאשתו במקום יבם מהו? Ha-mezakeh get l'ishto bimkom
yavam, mahu? He gives a גט get to his wife through another
person, that's what מזכה mezakeh means, in the place of a brother-in-law.
מהו? mahu? What do we do? Do we say, כיון דסניא לה,
keivan d'sanya lah, maybe because we can assume that the wife hates
the brother-in-law, זכות הוא לה, z'chus hu lah, that would be to
her benefit, וזכין לאדם שלא בפניו, v'zakin l'adam shelo b'fanav, and you
can merit somebody not in their presence, so you could represent my
wife not in her presence because it would be to her benefit.
או דילמא כיון דזימנין דרחמא ליה, O dilma keivan d'zimnin d'rachma lei,
but maybe there are times that a woman actually loves her brother-in-law
or likes him, וחוב הוא לה, v'chov hu lah, and she would
not want to be divorced as a way of getting out of
יבום, yibum, ואין חבין לאדם שלא בפניו, v'ein chavin l'adam shelo b'fanav,
and you cannot go ahead and hurt somebody not in their presence.
Now of course you could say why don't we look at each
individual circumstance and assess it? Right, the גמרא Gemara is trying to
maybe ask as a general rule, do we have a general rule
to make an assumption about whether this would be considered to somebody's
benefit or not? Can we assume that the wife generally does like
the brother-in-law or doesn't like the brother-in-law? Again, what you have to
add to this גמרא Gemara is that it's some context where the
guy is probably going to die or might die pretty soon. Otherwise
no matter how much she hates the brother-in-law, it doesn't mean she
wants to be divorced from her husband. Anyway, so let's take...
Well it said no, it asks both: possibly
oh you're right that's a good point it says זימנין דסניא ליה
Zimnin desanya leh I hadn't paid attention to that, but the first
case says זימנין דסניא ליה Zimnin desanya leh since she hates him
and the other way it says זימנין דרחמא ליה, Zimnin derachma leh,
sometimes she likes him. So that's a very good point that it
assumes the default is she probably hates him and that's why we're
assuming it should be for her benefit, but there might always be
scenarios where that's not true. Yeah, it's a very good close read,
yes.
So a man is concerned when he goes overseas or goes to
war, he gives a גט get and if neither of them have
relations then they can be remarried.
They can remarry unless he's a כהן, and then you have to
give a גט על תנאי get al tnai and so on. So
this is the thing that actually was done, but that's when the
woman was present, here she's not present. But Dov makes the very
accurate read that it's assuming she hates the guy and doesn't want
to do יבום, yibbum, and that's true continuing it's a whole מסכת
יבמות, Masechet Yevamot, here it's basically saying the default is she really
doesn't want to. But sometimes she's okay with it.
I mean the גמרא Gemara is kind of, well, when do we
like formally start to prefer חליצה? chalitzah?
Right,
so that's already an opinion in the גמרא. Gemara. But the reason
in the גמרא Gemara was not out of the concern for the
wife. It was concern that the man would do it שלא לשמה,
shelo lishmah, you know, but but yes, in אשכנז Ashkenaz they completely
adopt that you prefer חליצה, chalitzah, but that might have a lot
to do with the monogamous society. Right? So therefore חליצה, chalitzah, you
know, יבום yibbum you can't be talking too much about יבום yibbum
if it's a monogamous society. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So that's the question: do we say that sometimes however maybe
it's not to her benefit? ואין חבין לאדם שלא בפניו. Ve'ein chavin
leadam shelo befanav. אמר ליה, Amar leh, so he said back to
him, תנינא, tanina, we taught in our משנה, Mishnah, וחוששין לדבריה וחולצת
ולא מתייבמת. vechoshishin lidvareiha vecholetzet velo mityabemet. It says that whether she
testifies in in the two cases in the משנה Mishnah to either
to get out of יבום yibbum or to be obligated in יבום,
yibbum, right? Remember there were two scenarios where she was changing her
status. One was to change her status to be obligated in יבום
yibbum and one was to get out. And in neither case do
we believe her. So since we don't believe her in either case,
it means sometimes she wanted we're concerned in either case she might
be lying, right? Which means sometimes she might be lying to get
into יבום yibbum and sometimes she might be lying to get out
of יבום, yibbum, which means there's no rule. That sometimes it's you
know there are scenarios that are this way and there are scenarios
that are that way, which is a you know fascinating way of
inferring that from the משנה. Mishnah. אמר ליה, Amar leh, he said
back to him, אמר ליה רבינא לרבא, Amar leh Ravina leRava, so
that was answer the question. We can't make a rule that it's
to her benefit. So therefore, now what if we know that she
really hates the brother-in-law? That's not clear, but we certainly can't make
a rule that it's to her benefit. אמר ליה רבינא לרבא, Amar
leh Ravina leRava, so רבינא Ravina said to רבא, Rava, המזכה גט
לאשה במקום קטטה מהו? hamizakeh get leishah bimekom ketatah mahu? How about
the husband and wife are fighting, right? And they've been to see
a lawyer and they're whatever and there's all this animosity, and then
he gives a גט get to somebody for for her without her
being present and without her having assigned the person as as her
representative. So do we say since she's in the middle of this
big fight, clearly she would want the גט? get? מהו? Mahu? כיון
דאית לה קטטה בהדיה זכות הוא לה, keivan deit lah ketatah bahadeih
zechut hu lah, since she has a fight with him, it's definitely
to her benefit? או דילמא ניחא דגופא עדיף לה, O dilma nicha
degufa adif lah, or do we say even when a woman and
a husband are fighting, a woman still is not interested in divorce?
A woman still wants to be able to be with her husband.
Literally the pleasure or the benefit of her person is more important,
like to have a husband is more important to her even when
even when there's sort of animosity and fighting. Okay. תא שמע, Ta
shema, so come and hear, דאמר ריש לקיש, de'amar Reish Lakish, טב
למיתב טן דו מלמיתב ארמלו. tav lemetav tan du milemetav armalu. Better
to sit two together than to sit as a widow. Okay, which
is a very important statement in the גמרא, Gemara, that the גמרא
Gemara states this as a sociological sort of assessment, but you know
there was a big debate because with Rabbi Rackman and Rav Soloveitchik
about this because about using you know certain assumptions to allow for
giving of a גט get to a wife based on the fact
that oh in this case the woman definitely would want to be
divorced and the man would whatever and can you go ahead and
say our sociological realities are different from the גמרא? Gemara? And you
know Rav Soloveitchik took a very harsh stance against that but you
know anyway there's a lot of question about whether he whether his
statement was meant in as absolute ways as he said it. But
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is something that look you know
I mean is that women will settle much more than men will
settle. Okay. A woman will will marry a guy that she's not
so thrilled with or be happy to be married or whatever reconcile
herself to being married to somebody who is who's not so great
you know even because she'd rather because you know she'd rather be
married. And some people will say that that is you know that
that is tends to still be the case that women settle more
than guys. So anyway, טב למיתב טן דו מלמיתב ארמלו. tav lemetav
tan du milemetav armalu. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, דשומשמנא גברא. deshumshmana gavra.
Now we're going to get statements that reflect this type of attitude.
My husband could be an ant, דשומשמנא גברא, deshumshmana gavra, my husband
could be as small as an ant, כורסייה בי חרתא רמי, kursiyei
be charta rami, as long as like the you know the the...
my chair can be by the important people of the world. As
long as I can be married and have that status in society,
I don't care if my husband is a נעבעך. nebach. Okay, רב
פפא Rav Pappa אמר, רב פפא Rav Pappa states,
had the statement דנפצא גברא, denafsa gavra, my husband could be a
flax comber, but תיקרי בסיפי בבא ותיתיב, tikrei beseifei bava veteitiv, as
long as I get called to the you know to the to
the door of the house and I can sit down. As long
as I can be married, I don't care what my husband does.
רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר, דקולסא גברא, dekulsa gavra, my husband can
be—there's a question what this word means, I like the Soncino's translation
was cabbage head.
My husband could be a cabbage head, but לא בעי טלפי לקידרא,
lo baei talfei lekedira, as long as I don't need lentils for
the pot. As long as I'm married and he's bringing home the
food, I don't care what type of an idiot he is. Okay.
Yes, exactly. Right, exactly. תנא, tana, so we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, וכולן מזנות ותולות בבעליהן. vekulan mezanot vetolot bevaleihan. So all of
this basically is sort of like saying, you know, like, you know,
women are better than you know like there's a lot of נעבעך
nebach guys out there and the guys should be very appreciative that
women are willing to marry them even though they're so נעבעך, nebach,
because the societal realities are such that it's important for a woman
to be married. So it sort of gets women to settle more.
So if you would end it right here, it's like not saying
it's a good thing or whatever, but it's reflecting a societal reality
that men have really been like sort of are seen in a
negative light, you know, and the גמרא Gemara doesn't end on that
note. The גמרא Gemara ends on a note that sort of reverses
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, תנא, tana, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, וכולן מזנות ותולות בבעליהן. vekulan mezanot vetolot bevaleihan. If they
have husbands they don't like, they cheat on their husbands and then
when they get pregnant, they tell their husbands it's their kids. Okay,
so now all of a sudden what turned out to be like
the, you know, the sort of
more willingness of women and their good nature, I don't know the
good nature whatever anyway, the fact that they settle for for bad
guys, in the end they're the ones that are cheating and taking
advantage of the situation. As a result of this assessment, we can't
give a גט get to a wife even if she's fighting with
her husband because we say or we can't do it without her
presence because we say that we can't assume that she would want
a גט get in those cases because we assume that women more
want to be married. And I have to tell you that this
exerts a lot of whatever halachic issues I was alluding to before
with the רב and Rabbi Rackman, a lot of so a lot
of influence in perception issues because there are like a lot of
בתי דינים, batei dinim, you know, in Israel that a woman goes
and tells stories of abuse, abuse of her, physical abuse, sexual abuse,
hers, the kids or whatever, and the בית דין, beit din normally
a more חרדי chareidi based בית דין beit din will sort of
say like try to work it out or you know any type
of בית דין that says that they're deeply invested in שלום בית
shalom bayit is often a code term for they they absolutely will
resist any attempt at divorce. So it's always the point is we
gotta keep the family together. And part of that is influenced by
an idea, you know, so what if he's a lousy husband, you're
better off married, right? And this creates a real problem in terms
of a בית דין's willingness to be receptive to real problems in
the marriage and to be more you know proactive or responsive in
terms of areas of divorce. So, you know, we read this גמרא
Gemara and we laugh but, you know, but these things do shape
attitudes and we have to really acknowledge that. Okay, and with that
we will end and we have one פרק perek left to go.